The ultimate experience in gruelling terror.
The Evil Dead is a horror film directed by Sam Raimi.
In 1979, a group of college students find a Sumerian Book of the Dead in an
old wilderness cabin they've rented for a weekend getaway.
Ash, played by Bruce Campbell.
Cheryl, played by Ellen Sandweiss.
Scott, played by Richard DeManincor.
Linda, played by Betsy Baker.
Shelly, played by Theresa Tilly.
Fake Shemp, played by Philip A. Gillis.
The Evil Dead is a 1981 American independent supernatural horror film written
and directed by Sam Raimi (in his feature directorial debut).
The film stars Bruce Campbell, Ellen Sandweiss, Richard DeManincor, Betsy Baker, and Theresa Tilly as five college students vacationing in
an isolated cabin in the woods, where they find an audio tape that, when played, releases a legion of demons and spirits.
Four members of the group suffer from demonic possession, forcing the fifth member, Ash
Williams (Campbell), to survive an onslaught of increasingly gory mayhem.
Raimi, Campbell, producer Robert G.
Tapert, and their friends produced the 1978 short film Within the Woods as a proof of concept to build the
interest of potential investors, which secured US$90,000 to begin work on The Evil Dead.
Principal photography took place on location in a remote cabin in Morristown, Tennessee, in a
filming process that proved extremely uncomfortable for the cast and crew.
The film's extensive prosthetic makeup and stop-motion
effects were created by artist Tom Sullivan.
The completed film had its first, private screening for friends and family at the Redford Theatre in Detroit on October 15, 1981,
which attracted the interest of producer Irvin Shapiro, who helped screen the film at the 1982 Cannes Film Festival.
Horror author Stephen King gave a rave review of the film, which resulted in New Line Cinema
acquiring its distribution rights and giving it a wide theatrical release on April 15, 1983.
The Evil Dead grossed $2.4 million in the United States and $27
million overseas, for a worldwide gross of $29.4 million.
Both early and later critical reception were universally positive; in the years since its release, the film has developed a reputation as one of the most
significant cult classics, having been cited among the greatest horror films of all time, and one of the most successful independent films.
It launched the careers of Raimi, Tapert, and Campbell, who have continued to
collaborate on several films together, such as Raimi's Spider-Man trilogy.
The Evil Dead spawned a media franchise, beginning with two successors written and directed by Raimi, Evil Dead II (1987) and Army of Darkness (1992), a fourth film, Evil Dead (2013), which serves as a soft reboot
and continuation, a follow-up television series, Ash vs Evil Dead, which aired from 2015 to 2018, and a fifth film, Evil Dead Rise (2023); the franchise also includes video games and comic books.
The film's protagonist Ash Williams is considered to be a cultural icon.
The film explores themes of falsely accused, audio
tape, aggression, log cabin, friends.
The tone is dark.